<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a declaration of the Lords and Commons concerning the papers of the Scots commissioners, intituled The answer of the commissioners to both Houses of Parliament upon the new propositions of peace, and the foure bills to be sent to His Majesty / by Mercurius Pragmaticus.</title>
            <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36609</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15743704</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15743704</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104588</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52747)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104588)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1153:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a declaration of the Lords and Commons concerning the papers of the Scots commissioners, intituled The answer of the commissioners to both Houses of Parliament upon the new propositions of peace, and the foure bills to be sent to His Majesty / by Mercurius Pragmaticus.</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.S. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded. Pages 2-7 from defective Huntington Library copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Answer of the commissioners to both Houses of Parliament.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104588:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104588:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVER TO A DECLARATION OF The Lords and Commons, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Papers of the Scots Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>INTITULED, The Anſwer of the Commiſſioners to both Houſes of Parliament upon the new Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Peace, and the foure Bills to be ſent to his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Mercurius Pragmaticus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>J.S.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104588:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104588:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE late Declaration of the Lords and Commons, of the Parliament of ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>ALthough we are not ignorant how many obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions have of late been occaſioned, by thoſe who pretend a more then ordinary zeale to a ſpeedie ſettlement, and a compoſure of thoſe unhappy differences, which (but that the providence of the Higheſt prevailed) had ere this, buried the two Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> in an united ruine, yet we ſhall not waſte time now, to cite either the Impediments or the parties, contenting our ſelves onely with a free and full anſwer, to the late Declaration of the Lords, and Commons Aſſembled in the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> which we looke upon, as a meere bundle of invictives, and an heepe of Callumnies for through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole booke not one clauſe, but ſavours of malice, rancour and contempt, but indeed what elſe but gall, can flow from the quill, of that impudent Reviler of his King, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Incendiarie, between the two Kingdomes, <hi>Harry Martin,</hi> who (as we are credibly informed) was the compoſer of the ſaid Declaration, but we ſhall hold it; altogether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaneth us, to caſtigate Callumnies, of the ſaid <hi>Martin,</hi> in a publick way, and ſhall now proceed, to take to pieces, the late Declaration, to Diffect, and anotomize it, that ſo the whole proportion of it being open to the view of the world, they may be informed, of its imperfect perfectneſſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt then they Declare, that they were put upon this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104588:3"/>in anſwere to thoſe Papers intituled, <hi>The anſwer of the Commiſſioners of</hi> Scotland, <hi>to both Houſes of Parliament upon the new Propoſitions of peace, and four Bills to be ſent to his Majeſtie to undeceive the minds of the people of both Kingdoms,</hi> as if our fallacies were ſuch, that it is high time they were diſcovered, and that we had deceived our truſt, and by under hand and ſiniſter practiſes, ſought our owne and not our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons welfare, but we ſhall not need, to beſtow much labour, in wiping away the ſtaine, ſince our owne Nation are not the leaſt anxious of our fidelity, neither will it be a worke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the undertaking to releaſe their conſtant perfidiouſneſſe even from their firſt day of ſitting; and we ſhould but carry pots to Samos and Owles, to Athens, if we ſhould tell, they have betrayed their truſt to God, by breaking the Covenant, to their King by trampling upon the Oath of Allegiance, and to their Country, by proſtrating their power, and ſuffering themſelves to be over-awed, by a Sectarian Army, who are (or ought to be) wholy at their diſpoſing, but they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to brand us with Apoſtacie, but they alſo would give the world to thinke that our power is triviall, and invallid for they ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <q>We deſire it may be remembred, that when we ſpeake of the Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland,</hi> we intend not through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Declaration, the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> who we reſt confident will not owne their Commiſſioners in theſe Papers, in their tranſactions in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> nor in many other of their Papers, and proceedings when they ſhall be truly informed of their carriage, but that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland</hi> will be ready to doe us and themſelves right.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here they haue turned their Galls up, and ſpit the worſt of Venome, for becauſe themſelves would not be thought the leaſt guilty (as it hath everbeen the manner of perſons, the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104588:3"/>moſt nocent, and obnoxious) to ſtand high upon their reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they caſt aſperſions upon us and thinke themſelves ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently vindicated if we are diſparaged, in regard whereof we have a juſt occaſion, to returne to them their owne words according to their owne practiſes, and tell them, <hi>That all the Rhetorique uſed in this point, to abuſe the minds of well min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded people, and to heighten their fancies againſt our proceedinge might have been ſpared,</hi> but we ſee their aime, and that they have an ardeut deſire ſtill to keep themſelves in the Saddle had they ability, to mannage the Steed, and indeed to cauſe ſo implacable an hatred between the two Kingdomes, as all the Heccatombes, of after intreaties may not expiate.</p>
            <p>And that it may be ſo as ſoone as may be they proceed, to make their and our Soveraigne Lord King CHARLES, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of Governing, and themſelves of obeying, and this contrary to all law and reaſon they will prove with their wild Sophiſtrie to be both good and requiſite, when they ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <q>We aske what reaſon we have to reſpect better ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in the way of a treatie them formerly at <hi>Vxbridge,</hi> or in a perſonall treaty at <hi>Oxford,</hi> unleſſe wee be reſolved to Treat away all that we have fought for, and to be Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of what we could not be fought out of, or at leaſt what can we expect of a Treaty but under pretence of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying all intereſts, one intereſt ſhall be ſet up againſt an no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to devide us, and that thereby (having laid no founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſafety before hand the King might ſet up his intereſt above them all, if ſucceſſe, and advantage of the crowne in the Kings eſteeme muſt be the meaſure of our reſolutions, or that hereby we muſt have the way, or tearmes of our peace cut out unto us.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104588:4"/>
Thus they make themſelves no longer fellow ſubjects with us, and that by the right of conqueſt, as having our in pieces with the ſword, both the <hi>Covenant</hi> and the Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and ſo render themſelves to the world, as perſons who are no better then doubly perjuried; have they ſo ſoone, or elſe are they wicked as not to remember, how we once joyntly Soll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emnly proteſted with lift up hands to the moſt High God; that we had no intention to curtaile his Majeſtie of any of the leaſt of his lawfull Priviledges, but that with our utmoſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours we would aſſay to reinſtate his Majeſties in his Priſtine Glory and Dignitie, and having inſtated him to defend Him with our utmoſt abillities &amp; had we apprehended that the leaſt injurie or violence would have been committed againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Royall Perſon as it was offered at <hi>Holdenby,</hi> and repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be <hi>Hampton,</hi> or if we had not received a faithfull aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Houſes, that their intentions were cordial and Loyall towards him, not all the threatnings, or allurments, in the world ſhould have perſwaded us, to have parted with his Majeſties Perſon, till all Armies had been disbanded and the peace of the Kingdome ſetled, it was our brotherly confidence in the Houſes, who are (or ought to be) our fellow ſubjects, that moved us to ſurrender the King into their hands and therefore all the world cannot but aſſoile us and acknowledge our innocence and fidellity to the King; and that when wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him into the hands of theſe Commiſſioners appointed for that purpoſe, by both Houſes, of Parliament we had no thought not were left privie to their treacherous intentions towards him, but that we were then we are now his Loyall humble ſubjects, willing to ſubmit to all his lawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands with ſubmiſſive obedience, as to, our King and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</p>
            <p>But they goe on in their cavills, and would indeavour to prove by Sophiſtria, that which they have no warrant for, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by law or conſcience, when they tell us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104588:4"/>
               <q>Wee ſay that that the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſiones miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take their aime, if they thinke the Kings preſence with the Parliament, neceſſarily implieth his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence at <hi>London,</hi> which he and they ſo much deſire, that he might have oppertunity, to cajole the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens; if his preſence with the Parliament were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, yet it is not neceſſary, the Parliament be at <hi>London,</hi> and as much doe they miſtake the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Declarations, if they thinke it was the Kings Locall abſent from his Parliament which they Declared to be the chief cauſe of all the warre miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheif, and callamities of the Kingdomes, any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then it was his diſtance from them, in affections and his oppoſitions, to their counſells, and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What odd Silogiſmes are here, let the world judge, whether the Houſes, were it in their power, would not take away Monarchicall Government, Roote, and Branch, although it be the very baſis, whereon ours and their Priviledges are built, and the maine pillar that ſupporteth the Parliament Houſe, the Devill is a good Sophiſter, and dictates notably unto them, <hi>if the Kings preſence be neceſſary at London, yet it is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary the Parliament ſhould be at London,</hi> as if the Kings preſence at London, and ſiting amongſt them, in a Parliamentarie way could prove the Cajoling, of the Citizens who we believe are now become ſo weary of their tyranie, that they would be glad to be once more under his Majeſties command, were he in the ſame poſture of governing, that he was ere they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104588:5"/>began the warre, rather then to continre any longer, under a conſtrained obedience to them, but what maketh their averineſſe a miracle, is becauſe his Majeſtie hath been graciouſly pleaſed to proffer the ſigning to an act of Oblivion, and is content to cover all former impieties, under his owne skirts, but it ſeemes to us (and ſurely to all honeſt men) more then monſtrous that the Houſes who once told us it was their chiefe ſorrow that the King would not ſit with them, and made the world believe as they perſwaded us, that the cauſe of their warre, was to recover his perſon amongſt them, ſhould now publiſh to the world that his preſence amongſt them, is utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unneceſſary, as if it were poſſible toperſwade us or any poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſence, that they who were called together by him, act all in his name and becauſe of his diſtance from them, have done nothing theſe ſeven yeers, to prove they are a Parliament, ſave (perhaps) to defend themſelves; and to command in his name, ſhould now on the ſudden be inriched with ſo much power, from whence derived none knowes as without him to make lawes and Statutes unleſſe they intend (which wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe Heaven hinder them from) to depoſe him, and illegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate his children, but the truth is, for ought we ſee, or can ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by their fore paſſe actions and preſent proceedings, they never intend to ſettle the Kingdome, either with him or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him with him (it ſeemes) they dread to doe, being conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of their own guilt, and without him they cannot, nay but ſhall not doe it, while we are a Nation, but had not their conſciences been ſeared with an hot Iron, they might ere this have been reconciled to their King, and he to them, the Royall party apperſed, the Citie quitted the Country contented, and every man ſitting under his owne Vine would their wickedneſſe have permitted them, to have done ſo much good for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their Nation, how often have we ſued unto them to pity their owne, and the Kingdomes eſtate, how often have we implored them, that there might be a free and unreſtrained application made to his Majeſtie from the Parliaments of both Kingdomes deſiring them to invite his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to come to London, and to declare that he ſhould be there with ſafety honour and freedome then which we ſee, no other probable means to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a ſafe and well grounded peace, and this is no more then they and we are obliged to doe, according to our Covenant Allegiance, and duty of ſubjects.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104588:5"/>
But now we ſee, and it is too apparant to the world, that they reſpect not either Religion, the Intereſt of the Crown, or the Union and joynt concernment of both Kingdomes; and becauſe we charged them, and that upon good grounds, to tolerate all Religions, and to be remiſſe in looking after the matters of God; They ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <q>What are thoſe matters which theſe Commiſſioners call the matters of God? Are they the names <hi>Solemne League and Covenant,</hi> or the things contained in the Solemne League and Covenant? And if ſo, why not one thing aſwell as another? Why are not the Priviledges and Authoritie of Parliament, formerly acquieſced in, as the ſureſt Pillars and preſervatives of Religion? And why are not the Rights and Liberties of the Kingdome matters of God, as well as the Government of the Church, in ſuch and ſuch a forme? Of old the Clergie ſtiled their Temporalities and Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the Patrimony of Chriſt, and the quarrell betweene them and the State the Cauſe of God, and a matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, though indeed it was a conteſt onely of power and dominion, which indeed, if it be well looked into, will prove alſo the ſtate of many queſtions, which goe under the notion of Religion at this day.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What a moſt learned evaſion doe they here make, to juſtifie their breach of Covenant? Doe they thinke theſe quodlibets will anſwer the expectations, or ſettle the hearts of an incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Nation? It ſeemes by this, that when they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to League with us, they ſwore with a mentall reſervation, and intended to make application in ſuch manner as might moſt make for their owne advantage; If they keepe up their extorted power without diminution, if they attempt with their utmoſt indeavours, to make themſelves abſolute and Arbitrary Lords; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and be their under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> famous, we muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104588:6"/>with all willingneſſe, they give us a ſtrong motive, which is, The Priviledges of Parliament ought to be acquieſced in, as the ſureſt Pillars and preſervatives of Religion: ſo that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they pleaſe to call the Rights and Liberties of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, be it either in Impriſoning their King, or in tolerating a hodge-podge of all Religions; or be it in inſlaving and trampling upon their fellow Subjects, it muſt be tearmed with no worſe title then the matters of God; but they doe very notably, to make the cuſtome of the old Clergie their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (though they would not have us to thinke ſo) ſince with them they call all Cauſes Gods, provided they be feeling cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and make either for their profit or preferment; in regard whereof, we cannot but tell them, that they are the vileſt Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, we ſay not Treachers, that live, and that never men like them ever ſhew'd themſelves in ſuch various colours, while according to their owne ſaying of others, they ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſtrive to purchaſe a perfect Reformation, when indeed, it is only a conteſt of power &amp; Dominion, and a little to vary from their words, will prove alſo the ſtate of all their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings which goe under the notion of Religion: but they proceed to juſtifie (as, what is it that they will not defend?) And becauſe we are ſo credulous, they hope to perſwade us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a beliefe of any thing; And therefore they ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <q>It is one thing to leave every man without any Law to his own judgment and fancy, in the ſervice and worſhip of God, and another thing to give a Libertie by Law (as was deſired) to ſome men to doe ſome things in their owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not unlawfull, though different from what is thought fit to be generally ſetled in the Kingdome; it is one thing to require conformitie to a Law already made, according to the word of God; and upon cleare evidence thereof, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, to make a Law requiring conformitie from all perſons, to all things, though not founded upon any cleare evidence of Scripture, or that are only founded upon pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall grounds, wherein the Magiſtrate hath the like latitude to diſpenſe and qualifie, as to injoyne and ordaine; it is one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104588:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>thing what a State holds ſit to declare requiſite, and alſo to countenance and encourage by rewards; and other wayes, and another thing, when it holds fit to compell and force.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Wee confeſſe, That there is ſome difference between com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion and permiſſion, and that a <hi>Free State</hi> (which epethite wee hope the Houſes will not, nor dare not aſſume to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) may upon prudentiall grounds tolerate a Libertie in the worſhip of God; but all this while wee are confident, that they cannot doe ſo and not be guiltie of grievous ſinne; for who is ſo ſhallow not to conceive, or ſo obſtinate not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that where ſuch a toleration is granted, many Propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations muſt inevitably follow? For who ever knew or read, but that when men are permitted to worſhip God in their owne way, without limitation or preſcription, they for the moſt fall in one error or other? but wee perceive, that the Houſes, ſo themſelves may be tolerated, to ſit and ſway with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſturbance, care not what Religion their Vaſſailes are of; as the Turkes, who, ſo their ſlaves performe their ſervice, mind not whether they call upon Chriſt or <hi>Mahomet;</hi> nor care they, though by their impious toleration a doore be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Atheiſme and all Religions, to all kind of Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to Deformitie, and Multiformitie of Hereſies and Sects, which may produce the ruine of Religion in both Kingdoms: What a groſſe abſurditie is it of them, yea, worthy to bee laught at, to make a Law for the eſtabliſhing of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Government, and yet in the ſame Act to deſire that none ſhould obey that Law, but ſuch as are pleaſed ſo to doe? and againe, to appoint the Miniſters and Elders by an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to ſuſpend from the Sacrament onely ſuch perſons as the Houſes have thought fit and no other, though it be againſt their conſcience ſo to doe, and that they are bound with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſtrictions in their meetings and aſſemblies, and are not allowed the uſe and exerciſe of all the ordinances, appointed by the word of God; ſo as that Libertie of Conſcience is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to them, and granted to others who have an unlimited toleration for the time of indurance, matter of worſhip, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104588:7"/>exerciſe of all Ordinances; which toleration is of that capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie and latitude, that it admits of many vile and groſſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, which have beene condemned and caſt out of the Church in former times. And now for the nice diſtinction that they make concerning their owne powers as Magiſtrates, to countenance or compell as they find cauſe, it is cleare both by the word of God and humane examples, that a tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ought not to be permitted, and that the events of ſuch countenancings and encouragements as they ſpeak of, have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver produced ſad and fatall events. But all this while they have but proved themſelves Apoſtates, and relinquiſhers of thoſe Principles which they once bound themſelves to proſecute, and therefore muſt expect fierce vengeance and condigne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments hereafter.</p>
            <p>But becauſe wee once demanded of them, according to our dutie to God, and allegeance to our Soveraigne, whether a To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration ſhall be continued to all ſuch, as by their pernicious Doctrines and Actions offer violence to the Kings Perſon and Authoritie, and in a high degree violate every Article of the <hi>Solemne League and Covenant;</hi> they ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <q>That neither to all ſuch, nor to any ſuch, is a Toleration deſired: but who doe more undermine the Securitie of the Kings Perſon and Authoritie, then thoſe that hinder a happy Settlement betweene him and his People, by a cauſeleſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting from the Houſes of Parliament, in thoſe few neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie things deſired by them, as previous to a Treatie upon the reſt, and that boulſter him up in Counſels and Reſolutions ſo apparantly deſtructive to himſelfe, his Authoritie, and Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, who ſo highly have invaded the Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the caſes of particular Members thereof?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Were it ſo, as the contrarie is too apparant, that no ſuch Toleration be deſired; yet ſure it well becomes loyall and faithfull ſubjects ſtrictly to forbid and prohibit all ſuch wilde courſes. But it is apparant, yea (and to our ſhame) is become the talke of forraigne Nations, that they not onely tolerate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104588:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>but encourage their Independent Miniſters, on all occaſions and oportunities, to rayle againſt their Soveraigne, to ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize his fore-paſt Acts of Government, and to exaſperate the people againſt Monarchicall Diſcipline. Nor is this impietie permitted in Pulpits alone, but alſo frequently in Print, while their Pamphleters are countenanc'd to rayle againſt him, as a vile and unworthy man, one not meet to ſway the Scepter; a man of bloud, who ought to be called to an account for thoſe Cruelties that were practiſed during the Warre.</p>
            <p>But this wee have no reaſon to marvell at, ſince the Houſes themſelves have given thoſe Varlets ſo pregnant an example to imitate, as appeares by a <hi>Declaration</hi> put forth in their Names, and intituled, <hi>A Declaration of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament, ſhewing the Reaſons and Grounds why they have voted, that no more Addreſſes be made to the King, nor any Meſſage received from him.</hi> And although it doth wonderfully aſtoniſh us to thinke, that ſo illegall and deſtructive a Vote ſhould ever be, yet wee cannot but wonder much more, that ſo ſtrange a Paradox ſhould be maintained in Print, and that by the appointment of the Houſes, ſince wee and the world know, that that diſloyall Vote was againſt the very eſſence and being of Parliaments; and that when they Voted no further Addreſſes ſhould be made to the King, they Voted themſelves no Parliament, if they will credit the fundamentall Lawes of their Land. But our ſoules are ſmitten with ſorrow, and with unſpeakable horror, when wee cogitate the matter and ſubſtance of that <hi>Declaration;</hi> wherein the Houſes (ſwayed by wee know not what Furies) have not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to tax his Majeſtie as acceſſarie to the poyſoning of his Father; a thing not to be thought on, and from which wee are confident his Majeſtie is as cleare as hee was at the houre of his Birth: as alſo they charge him to have a hand in the Buſineſſe of <hi>Rochel,</hi> with other Crimes and Miſdemeanours, in ſuch contemptuous and diverſivolent language, that wee have cauſe to ſuſpect they are mad, and by ſome fatall accident are bereft of their wits. But wee would faine know of them, ſince themſelves can ſo eaſily diſpenſe with all Oathes and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, and have caſt behind them all the dutie and allegiance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104588:8"/>they owe unto their Soveraigne; whether, or no, wee his ſubjects of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhall be prohibited by them from making any further Addreſſes to, or receiving a Meſſage from him? For how ere they (elated with their ſucceſſes) are pleaſed to taunt us, as contemptible; yet wee would have them know, that wee eſteeme our ſelves equally intereſſed in the perſon of the King; and though he be in their repute but a <hi>dead Dog,</hi> yet he is in our ſight a <hi>living Lion.</hi> But whereas they ſay, and that in reference to us, That <hi>none more undermine the Securitie of the Kings Perſon and Authoritie, then thoſe that hinder a happie Settlement betweene Him and His People, by a cauſeleſſe Diſſenting:</hi> Wee anſwer; What diſ-affection did they ever finde in us? If they have, let them divulge it, as wee are ſure they would not have forgotten to doe, had they had the leaſt colour or pretext: But wee perceive the ground of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice is, for that wee joyned not with them, and were not ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent upon his Majeſtie for the ſigning of the laſt foure Bills; which Bills were deſtructive to Religion, his Majeſties Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and the Amitie of the two Kingdomes; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we could not in Conſcience or Honour joyne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them: eyther let them ſay how and by what meanes wee boulſter him up in Counſels and Reſolutions, apparantly deſtructive to himſelfe, his Authoritie, and Poſteritie; if they meane; that our Proteſtations to be loyall ſubjects unto him, according to Gods command, and the Oath that wee have taken, be a boul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of him, then wee muſt tell them, that wee doe but our dutie, and what they ought to doe, were they not Rebellious; and wee feare their owne wickedneſſe doth ſo boulſter up themſelves, that they will goe in a trance to Hell, and ſinke ere they are aware of it: But their Conqueſts doth ſo puffe them up, that they imagine themſelves ſafe even from the Arme of Heaven; and they reſolve (it ſeemes) ſince they have brought their King on his knees, not to pardon him, though he beg it, nor to ſmile upon him, though he kiſſe the Rod; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they tell us:</p>
            <p>
               <q>We ſay, the King having ſtood it out to the laſt, and being reduced to the condition he is in, the Houſes making ſo often
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104588:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>applications unto him; and after all, making him ſuch an Offer, as upon his granting them, thoſe few neceſſary things (which upon no tearmes, nor upon any Treatie, they can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede from) to treat upon all the reſt, affordeth a greater and more ſolid ground of confidence to the King, then any thing he can doe for the Parliament doth give them; for what can he give them, but what they have alreadie?</q>
            </p>
            <p>That the King ſtood it out to the laſt, none can denie; but that he ſhould be reduced to the condition he is in, we are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to ſeeke: we grant, the Houſes made ſeverall applications to the King, but their Propoſitions were too high, and (indeed) ſo deſtructive to his Majeſties power, that we ſee not how he could either in Conference or Honour ſigne them: but for the foure laſt Bills, the Houſes had learnt by their former applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and they knew right well, that his Majeſtie would by no meanes aſſent to them, for that (to ſpeake truth) they were meerly Impoſitions, and not Propoſitions; and to us it ſeemeth, they rather deviſed them as an occaſion to quarrell with him, that ſo they might have ſome pretence to Vote as they did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, rather then out of any reall intent that his Majeſtie ſhould ſigne them, and ſo a perſonall Treatie enſue. But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they boaſtingly ſay, that the King can give them nothing but what they have alreadie; Wee anſwer, That there is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vaſt difference betweene an uſurpt fruition, and a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble legall injoyment: 'Tis truth, they have now his Revenue, his Navie, Caſtles, and Magazine, wholly in their own hands, but can that take them off from yeelding obedience to his lawfull commands, or make him uncapable of exerciſing his Kingly power? Surely no: God Almightie open the hearts of the two Houſes, that they may conſider and repent them, and let them know, that wee will leave no way or meanes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attempted, to reſtore our Soveraigne to his full, and former power and greatneſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
